嘿嘿嘿，这里是STH的Patrick
hey guys this is patrick from sth
今天我会介绍一些会让你大开眼界的东西
today we're probably going to blow a lot of people's minds with what we're going to
我们先具体说说看是这一代的数据是如何存储的
show you specifically let's talk about how storage is done for generations
这一代服务器使用2.5英寸硬盘位
you've had servers with like two and a half inch storage bays those storage
其中包括SATA、SAS，当然还有NVME硬盘
bays have had sata they've had sass they've also had nvme drives and the
最主要的思想是把他们接入含有SAS HBA，或者RAID卡的存储服务器
basic idea is that you take your drives you put them into the storage server you have something like a sas hba raid
或者通过NVME直连主服务器
controller or you just have nvme connections to the main server the main
这些服务器一般都是双路x86，比如XEON或者EPYC
server is usually an x86 server with two intel xeon cpus or amd epic cpus just
或者一些别的差不多的东西
something like that and then basically
下一步人们会把存储接入网络，使得所有别的设备都能访问到存储
what's the next step well we have to go put that storage onto the network so all the rest of our infrastructure can talk
同时为了使能连接到网络，服务器得添加网卡
to it so then we have some network cards
这些卡不管是光纤卡、以太网卡还是IB网卡
those network cards even if they're fibre channel adapters or they're just traditional ethernet adapters infiniband
都得从服务器后面连接到网络中
whatever you have well basically you need to have those kind of network adapters on the back of the system and then that basically goes out to your
在某些方面看，这样的做法很愚蠢
network and in some ways that's stupid
我这样说的理由是这样的结构有太过多的转换了
right the reason i say it's stupid is because well think about how many conversions you have right you have
你看看，硬盘插进机箱的背板里，接入到x86服务器，做一些处理后
drives and then you put them into a chassis which goes into a backplane that backplane then goes to an x86 server which has to do something on that and
再通过网络传输后，转换到PCI-e 信号，脱离以太网
then from there it basically has to go over the network and so you have to do another translation to pcie back over
最后才能进入系统。
the network and now we're basically out onto ethernet and then it has to go into the system frankly that's kind of a
说实话由于这些不同的转换，这是一个非常奇怪的过程
really weird way to go do it because that's a lot of different translations
因此，铠侠为了解决这个问题生产了这款叫em6的SSD
and so what kioxia has is actually something called the em6 ssd you might
我以前听说过cd6和cm6，这款em6和别的“6”有什么区别呢？
say em6 i've heard of cd6 cm6 i mean i've heard of lots of these different sixes like what's different with this
区别在于其中的“e”代表了以太网(Ethernet)
and the difference is the fact that there's an e which stands for ethernet
也许不是这样的，但是这正是我要说的
maybe it doesn't but that's what we're going to say it stands for and the
em6和其他ssd相比如此与众不同的原因在于
reason that those em6 ssds are so much different from pretty much anything else
他们完全不同
that you've seen is really just the fact that they are different they actually
em6使用的协议不是NVME，或者说与外部互联的协议其实25g以太网
speak instead of nvme they speak or their external connectivity is actually 25 gig ethernet so when you plug that
所以当你把SSD塞入机箱插电开机的时候
ssd into a chassis to get power and cooling for example instead of it going
em6不会通过PCI-e通道和CPU通信很多次 ，而是直接连接到交换机里面去
over pcie a whole bunch of times into cpus it directly goes into a network
现在你可能会在心里想：“Patrick，这东西理论上听起来不错，实际如何工作的呢？”
switch now you might be thinking hey patrick that sounds theoretical and great but like how does it actually work
“要怎么拿它组阵列？为什么我要用它来代替原来的？”
what do we do about raid like like how does this hold like why why would i even
我想了想应该这样
do this and so i thought about that and
我应该先向你们展示一下下一代存储应该是怎样
i said hey what if what if i actually went and showed you guys the next generation of how you might do storage
所以我去到加利福尼亚州圣何塞的铠侠实验室
and so what i did was i traveled to san jose california so i could go to the lab
来向你们展示这是个什么玩意
at kioxia and just kind of show you guys what is going on here because this is definitely a newer generation so for the
视频剩下的部分我们将出发到那里去。
rest of this video we're going to get on the road and if it sounds a little different it's because we're on the road
好的，现在我们已经到了铠侠的实验室
okay so here we are in the kioxia lab and
我们来看看这台Ingrasys出品的服务器
we are going to take a look at the ingrasys system now this is something
其实我们之前已经看过它好几遍了
that we have actually looked at a number
比如说在SC21上
of times this particular system we looked at it specifically at SC21 and
它的外观基本和常见的存储服务器差不多
what you can basically see is that this looks like something that we've seen a bunch of times in terms of storage
它高度为2u，有24盘位
systems there's a 2u 24 bay chassis and
光从前面看你可能会说“我之间看过这东西”
from the front frankly you wouldn't be wrong to say hey i've seen this type of box before
但是严谨地来说，这并不是一个机箱
however that is not exactly the case because
虽然从前面看上去这些只是质量不错的硬盘托架
when you look at the system while we have these nice drive trays when we pull one of the drives out what you're gonna
实际上这里面插的都是em6和一块小小的红色板子
see is that well there's an em6 drive in there and this funky little red board
我们接下来会仔细聊聊这部分
we're gonna get into exactly what's going on here in a moment but the big
但其中最重要的是这是一片可以提供和普通u.2形态的NVME硬盘一样功能的SSD
thing here is that this is serviceable like a normal nvme ssd or u.2 ssd or something like
可以说它和NVME硬盘几乎是一样的，且可以热插拔
that right this is pretty much the same these are hot swappable and well i guess
接下来的问题又来了
the next question is how what makes this
这套系统有什么不一样的地方？
system different and why do we even care
我们要关心em6的哪些地方呢？
about this whole em6 thing and so here
这是一张在盘架里的em6的照片
is basically the picture of the drive in a sled and what you're going to see is
要注意到的是这里的两个edsff连接器
that we have this em6 drive and then we have two connectors which are actually edsff connectors so these are the same
所以你基本上可以把它当成e1.s 或者e3.s硬盘
ones you'd see in like e1.s or something like e3.s drives or something
或者其他有edsff标准接口的硬盘
like that you'd see these edsff connectors and there are two of them
双端口在拓扑中非常重要
which is really important when we actually look at the topology there's
此外，还有另一个版本的板子和导轨套装
also a little version of this that has a
可以容纳NVME SSD
sled and has the space for a nvme ssd so
所以你可以直接拿普通的NVME SSD放进去
you can actually take a normal nvme ssd
放到这个神奇的小控制板上
put it into this little marvel
controller board and this will actually
以此来把硬盘变成NVMEof硬盘
turn it into an nvme over fabric ssd so
只要你想，你完全可以拿手边就有的SSD这么干
you can totally use a different ssd if you want it's just that's what we have
看这张图，你可能会发现这块硬盘有两个不同的MAC地址
here now something you are going to notice is also the fact that these drives say two different mac port
分别属于端口0和端口1
numbers there's port zero and port one
一块盘有两个MAC的原因其实是这是块双端口硬盘
there's two different macs because these are actually dual port drives these are
这个设计来源于SAS
really going after sas and to be going
因此你得为这种设备提供两个路径来连接
after sas or dual nvme you actually need to have dual paths to a given storage
巧的是我们手上正好有双端口edsff连接器
device so what we basically have is we have those two edsff connectors and when
好戏在接通电源后才刚刚开始
we get to the nodes powering them this is where some of the real magic happens
精彩程度远超物理接口带来的刺激
way beyond the physical interface or
我们现在看到的是一堆接口
anything like that what we actually have is a bunch of connectors but you're
但奇怪的是这些接口只有一排
gonna see that we only have one row of connectors on this node and that is
那是因为我们实际上有两个控制器节点，但严谨地说它们又不叫“控制器”
because we actually have two controller nodes but they're not controller nodes
不像是我们平常在x86服务器里面看到的那种控制器
like you'd have in an x86 server or a
也不像是通常的存储阵列里面的控制器
standard storage array when you look at
转头从后面看这套系统的时候，你可以看到两个冗余的通道
the back of the systems you can actually see that we have the two different redundant paths and at the back we
表面上看就是几个巨大的100G，或200G之类的端口
basically just have just giant network ports you can run something like 100 gig networking or 200 gig networking or whatever you want on the back of it you
此外还有外带管理接口
also see that we have an out-of-band management port and all the kind of
还有usb口之类的。这些接口通常出现在交换机上，用来升级
things that we normally see from a switch because we also have a usb port for things like upgrades and then we
顺便还有一个console口
have a a console port as well so we have basically everything that you would have in a switch and that's because inside
这些接口之所以存在，是因为这个节点从内部看基本就是个交换机
these nodes what we actually basically have is a switch and so here's another
这张图是我在SC21上看到的一个版本
version of the one that we saw at supercomputing 21 and you're going to
可以清楚地看到后面的口都是100G以太网端口
see that we have all of the ports on the back and these are all 100 gigabit
这个版本他们给接口上了色，实验室里给我们看的那个没有
ethernet ports they have colors in this version they don't have colors in the lab version that we saw at Kioxia
这两者之间还是有一点小区别
have just a little difference in terms of you know the lab version versus the one that we actually saw on the show
这张图是整个系统从机架里搬出来的样子
floor here's the front of the system out
当然上面还是有块有机玻璃
of a rack so you just kind of see it and it actually has a plexiglass top so you can see kind of back where
这样能让你了解硬盘和节点之间的位置关系
the node sits versus the drives and the
硬盘托架那么长的原因有两个
reason that the drive bays are that long is for two reasons one so that way you
第一个，能让你用转接器来把普通的NVME SSD转换为NVMEof 以太网设备
can actually go and put you know the adapter and convert a nvme ssd to a nvme over fabric ethernet device and
当然你也可以只用这个机箱，它有另一个版本，里面可以装
edsff SSD then also you could also use this chassis if you wanted to with a version of this that has edsff so you could just use
组装成一台普通的NVME服务器
this as a normal nvme server like you normally would if you had different nodes so this is actually something that
Ingrasys把它打造地非常灵活
ingrasys makes that is super flexible
如果你不知道Ingrasys是哪家公司，它其实是富士康的子公司
and if you don't know Ingrasys are actually a division i think of foxconn
这是一家非常大的供应商企业
so a big big provider there and the
总之，你可以把它当作传统的NVME服务器
whole idea here is that you could have a version of this that is really just a standard old school nvme server or the
也可以把他作为基于以太网的NVMEof设备
other version of it is this which is the nvme over fabric ethernet version now i
这台淡然是以太网版的，看看它的内部
mentioned the fact that this is an ethernet version and when you look inside the system this is definitely a
这完全就是一台交换机
switch guys this is not you know something else this is a switch so under
这个巨大的散热器下面的是交换芯片
the big heatsink it's actually the switch chip in this version it's
这个版本的芯片是Marvell的
actually a marvell switch and then what
接下来是一个m.2 SSD
you're gonna see is that you'll see an
是交换机的存储
m.2 ssd and that's your storage for the
黑色散热器下面的是一个x86 cpu
switch now under the black heatsink you can see that we have an x86 cpu and then
以及一条单通道内存
we have a single channel of memory and
这个cpu运行控制方案
that's really running the control plan
交换机本身运行的是SONiC系统
now when we look in the switch itself what you can actually see is that this whole switch is running sonic so this is
运行微软Azure的SONiC平台算是当下软件定义网络的标配了
running you know the big microsoft azure sonic platform that is like the number one thing in software-defined networking
SONiC作为时下热门交换机系统，运行在很多SDN网络中
right now it is you know all kinds of hotness it's definitely what we like to go run on a lot of our switches and so
在这里你可以用软件定义网络来控制数据流进出SSD
you're basically using software-defined networking to go and control the data flows to and from the nvme ssds and just
另一个比较好玩的是
another really quick kind of fun one
终端上的这些输出显示我们正通过telnet连进SSD
here this little bit right here is where we're actually telnetting into a ssd so
想想看，我们正用telnet
think about this for a sec we are
通过网络 连进NVMEof SSD
telnetting over the network to a nvme over fabric ssd what in the heck is
真是太疯狂了
going on here this is absolutely crazy
我们来介绍一下这一切是怎么办到的吧
and we're gonna get into what's going on in a second so let's go and hop in and
我们开了一个demo来进行演示
just kind of show you a demo of what this looks like so now we're on a
我们现在在工作站中，我们想要连接到网络中的NVME硬盘
workstation and we're going to connect to these nvme drives that are just sitting on the network and they're sitting on
就是刚刚展示的这些插在Ingrasys交换机里面的硬盘
that switch in that that chassis that the ingress chassis that we just showed
我们将会通过网络去访问它们
you we're just going to go and access them over the network so the first thing
接下来我想要列出nvme设备
that we are going to do is we're going to have to you know we have right now you can see that with the nvme list we
但可以看到一个都没有出来
don't have any nvme drives at all on the
接下来我们来让他们出现在这里
system but we're going to do is we're
先ping一下我们刚刚telnet进去的硬盘
going to go ping that host that we just telnet it into the next thing that we're
我们要来寻找一下它们
going to do is we're going to discover
我们要指定使用RDMA，RoCEv2，以及NVME硬盘的地址
and we're specifically going to use rdma in RoCE v2 and then we're going to
这样我们就连上了一个em6 SSD
connect to the nvme drive so we're going to connect to a single em6 ssd right now
它们之间的连接完全是网络，没有存储服务器，而是直连那边的交换机
purely over the network there's no storage server it's only connected to the network switch in that chassis and
现在通过lsblk命令就能看到硬盘了
now what you can actually see with lsblk is that we can actually see that the
名字叫nvme0n1
nvme drive is connected so that's nvme0n1
第二步来创建文件系统
but then the next step is that we are going to make a file system on
一般来说这都是非常重要的
that because that's usually pretty important to go do okay so here we are
那我们在那个不接存储服务器，直连以太网的NVME硬盘上创建一个xfs文件系统吧
making an xfs file system on that nvme drive that's not connected to a storage server only to ethernet now when we do
我们先用nvme list，你能看到一块3.84T的SSD
nvme list you can see that we have the 3.84 terabyte ssd and you can see that
现在正在创建xfs文件系统
we are now making a xfs file system on that and
再次强调，这块硬盘是直接连接到网络中的
again this is not even over this is not a local drive this is just over the ethernet it's not connected to a storage server this is purely over ethernet directly to the drive itself the next
接下来我们挂载这一块硬盘
step is we will mount that single drive
我这里强调了“一块”硬盘，你可以猜猜看我下一步会干什么
and we're saying it's a single drive and you can guess we're going to go next with this
已经挂载好了
but there we can see that we actually have the drive mounted as a single drive
我们来试着拷贝一点文件
and now it's time to go copy some files
就把大便拷过去吧~
over let's go copy debian over and so we
正好有一个大便在那
just have a zip of debian and that's
好了，这样就拷贝好了
just being copied over the network and it's already done okay so that's like
以上是单盘版本的操作
the single drive version of this and
虽然看上去不错，但是问题是如何向外扩展呢？
while the single drive version is good the next question is well can't you scale out like what if you had a data
如果你有一数据中心的这东西
center of these you wouldn't necessarily
你肯定不会像这样只用一块硬盘
want to just go access one drive right
你肯定又一堆这样的硬盘
you might have a bunch of them and you'd want to go pull drives maybe from
也许数据会从数据中心的不同部分、不同机架、不同机箱中的硬盘里读取
different chassis different racks different parts of the data center
但我们不用考虑这些东西
whatever it is and we can just because
因为我们能把每个单独的硬盘作为一个NVME硬盘
we can treat each individual drive as
使我们能够把它们视作本机NVME硬盘
its own nvme drive that allows us to go
于是乎我们就能在这些硬盘中创建阵列
do things like we can do raid we can do
以及任何好玩的操作
all kinds of fun stuff so let's go look
那接下来我们看看创建阵列是怎么样的
at what that looks like and specifically
具体到实际，我们先来删掉之前我们连接的硬盘
we're gonna have to go and remove that first drive that we just put on there
我们来把它从系统中删掉
we're gonna go remove that from the system so that way
下一步我们直接用这个脚本来快速完成
this all works okay now we're gonna do is we're just gonna go script this real
这个脚本在干的是连接所有那边那个机器里面的硬盘
fast so it's uh pretty easy but the basic idea is we are going to connect to all of these nvme drives that are in a
这里用脚本的原因是你们肯定不希望看到我我一个一个地添加硬盘
chassis via a script and the reason we're using a script here is just because you don't want to see us add
毕竟我之前已经给你们演示过一遍了
drives individually but we already showed you the command for that so
敬请谅解
hopefully hopefully that makes sense
做完之后下一步就能创建RAID了
and once we do that the next step is we can actually go and we can create a raid
非常不错
array which is awesome and because
但是呃这里有点小问题
screwed up a little bit uh we only have
只有23个盘上线，但是一共有24个盘
23 of the 24 drives uh because there's a
这个脚本有点小问题
little script issue so that was a little
出了点出状况，大伙见谅
oops but you know you guys get the idea
我想说的是这里又23块3.84T硬盘
there's actually 23 basically 3.84 terabyte drives here so that gives us
总共给我们提供大约80T可用空间
roughly 80 terabytes or so usable and so
接下来我们来挂载阵列
then what we can do is we can mount the
挂载完毕，我们就有了一个巨大的80T硬盘
array and then once we've mounted the array we basically just have a giant 80 terabyte drive even though you wouldn't
虽然说你不一定要那么大的盘，或者那么大一块只提供给单个系统的硬盘
necessarily have an 80 terabyte drive or maybe an 80 terabyte drive within a system well now you can just go over the
但我刚才的演示让你能够通过玩过获取大量硬盘，用来创建阵列等等
network and just grab as many drives as you want and then create a raid array
现在我们再来把大便复制过去吧
with that and again we can just go copy our little debian zip over and
好了
there we go now the other thing that
以上就是我想要展示给各位看的
we're not showing here is just the fact
单台服务器不仅可以做一对一的直接映射
that not only can you just have a single drive to a single server and just do
你还可以用命名空间，把一个NVME硬盘切成片
that straight mapping you can also use namespaces and slice up a nvme target
把它们切成不同的分区，以提供给不同的系统使用
ssd that's on ethernet you can slice that up into multiple different little partitions and then give that to multiple systems and why that matters is
这个功能重要的原因是
you might want to only give say a bunch
每台机器有时候可能只在一个NVME设备上存一点点数据 比如100G
of machines only maybe i don't know 100 or so gigabytes worth of storage on each nvme device and then as they need more
如果需要更多空间，就会去不同的硬盘中取
storage you can just go pull in more storage from different devices that
这意味着你的数据会更加分散
means that your data is spread among
更多的设备意味着更多的你懂的优势
more drives and that allows you to have you know if you have
a number of drives allows you to have a larger number that
像是更强的性能，以及更好的容错
you're pulling from which gives you more performance and it also gives you the ability to manage failures and risk in
遇到特殊情况也能更好应对
that kind of situation and we can treat
我们还能把单独的一块硬盘视为独立个体
every single drive as its own independent thing because well i mean
因为我们能telnet过去还能ping它嘛
just like we can telnet and ping them
每块硬盘都是网络上的节点
each drive is its own node on the
我们不用穿越多种类型的存储系统
network and so we're not going across like multiple storage systems and we're
也不用升级存储系统
not really scaling up a storage system
我们只需要去升级这些以太网交换机就行了
all we're doing is using these you know chassis that are really the you know ethernet switch chassis and we're
比如升级交换机端口数
basically just scaling up the number of ethernet switches with ports that we
因为我们只需要通过网络就能直接访问这些资源了
have and then we're basically just accessing these resources directly over
由于它们管理升级都很方便
the network and so from a you know ease of management or ease of scalability standpoint this is like as easy as just
你只需要往上加交换机以及硬盘就可以了
adding more switches and adding more drives onto a network you're not having
不用像普通阵列一样“哦，我的硬盘数量多到了阵列支持的极限数量”
to expand your array you're not like oh no i've hit my array limit like your array limit is like how much can you
这台机器有多少ip就能寻址多少硬盘
address with uh with with networking um and how many ips do you have and all
总之这种东西的可拓展性太强了
that kind of stuff i mean it's like it's
like way way more scalable and so i think
这就是为什么大家伙都想要用这东西
that's why folks are really looking at
真是牛逼爆了
this and saying like this could actually be something that is super cool and i
现在我们要用PCI-e卡以及一整台服务器来运行阵列，但下一步
will just plug it real quick that we are using the pcie adapter and the system to go run that md raid but the next step of
下一步我们会用DPU来管理阵列以及其它所有基础设备
this of course is the fact that you could use DPUs and manage all the raid and all of the infrastructure with the
而不是用一整台工作站来干这件事
dpu instead of using the workstation
就像这张图中我们正在干的事情
like we're using here we're just doing
这张图是一张示意图，我希望你能通过这张图懂我的意思
that for demo purposes but hopefully you
兄弟们我希望你们喜欢这条对铠侠em6的介绍视频
get what's going on so guys i hope you like this look at the KIOXIA em6 nvme
这些SSD对我来说真是牛逼坏了
ssds i mean i know this to me at least was absolutely crazy to go see i've
我想要做这个demo整整一年了
wanted to do this demo for absolutely
总的来说，它的价值在于不需要一台x86或者arm服务器来把存储空间传递到
years but the basic idea here is that you don't necessarily need an x86 server to go or an arm server to actually go
另外的服务器那里去
and deliver your storage to your servers
这两者完全是不同的概念，显然是一种更加现代的存储方法
right i mean this is a totally different paradigm and it's definitely a more modern way to go and do storage you
这样一来存储管理员不再是必须的了
don't necessarily need storage admins as
网络管理员就可以确保数据正常传输
much as you basically just need network admins so that way you can keep the flow of data going the other thing is that
另外，每个NVME SSD都获得更高的使用效率
you can get a much higher utilization of the actual nvme ssds because you can
因为你是通过网络传输的数据，因此不会受到机箱内部带宽的限制
actually go access those nvme ssds over the network and you're not limited by the chassis bandwidth necessarily of an
如果使用x86服务器那必然会在服务器内部进行传输后，再从网卡出口
x86 server that has to go through another nic so you actually can get a
可见新架构会节约不少性能
lot more performance out of that and
你还能利用它干其他特别厉害的事情
then you can also do all kinds of things
比如说分片功能在这个拓扑下能实现的一些功能
like slice them up and do really just kind of cool things if you just kind of think about what the topology allows you
我希望你喜欢这套新一代存储系统
to do so i hope you really appreciate the fact that this is definitely a new generation of devices and what i really
但我想让大家想一想
think and really hoping just personally
如果没有这套系统
is that you take this away and you think
有没有什么其他的办法能够达到同样的效果
about what are the other ways that you could do this because the next thing
因为接下来我们将要展示如何用DPU，而不是以太网来办到这件事
that we're going to show is well how would you go manage this if you actually used dpus instead of just using ethernet
如果你的服务器里面有一块直连NVME SSD的DPU，可以像我展示的那样吗？
connected devices like what if you had a dpu in the server that is directly connected to the nvme ssds if you think
如果你认为不可能，那就等几天，我会来用事实闪爆你的狗眼
that sounds crazy just keep waiting for another couple days because we're going to have that and i think it's going to blow people's mind that is my real goal
当然这也是我做“下一代存储技术”这一系列视频的初衷
with this series and that is really to show you what some of the next generation storage technologies are going to look like because frankly
因为说实话我们用了三年又三年的设备真的烂透了
things like we've used for years just those are boring they're not necessarily
它们并不是人们发明过的最好的技术
the best and people have innovated since then and we have new technologies so
相比之下肯定有更好更新的方法
there are better and newer ways to go do
我做视频的目的是赶在你们花时间踩坑之前告诉你们
things and i just want to show you those before well you go down a path that maybe you don't necessarily want to or maybe you see something that you think
或者把它介绍给适合这个的方案的人
is like absolutely perfect for you so i
我只想把它展示给你看
just want to present that to you so with
谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢
that if you like this video well give it a like click subscribe turn on those notifications so you can see whenever we come out with great new videos as always
祝你有个开心+愉快的一天
thanks for watching have an awesome day